Guide to the Records of the Office of the Vice President and Secretary (Pollock, Thomas) RG 4.0.2
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Vice President and Secretary (Pollock)
Bulk, 1961-1966
1930-1967
RG 4.0.2
New York University Archives
2.085 linear feet
The collection comprises documents and correspondence originating from the Office of the Vice President and Secretary during the term of Thomas Pollock (1959-1966). The collection documents trips he took as a representative of that office to various other academic institutions; notes and documentation on various programs he supported or proposed, such as the British University Summer Schools and College of Independent Study; and documentation from boards and institutions of which he was a member, such as as the TIAA/CREF Board, and the Publishing Council of NYU Press.
New York University. Office of the Vice President and Secretary.
Pollock, Thomas Clark, 1902-1988
Biography of Thomas Pollock
Thomas Clark Pollock (1902-1988) served New York University in a number of capacities. From 1941 to 1943 and 1944 to 1947, he was Professor of Education and Chairman of the Department of English Education. He was Professor of English and Dean of the Washington Square College of Arts and Science 1947 to 1962. From 1951 to 1952 he took a leave of absence from his deanship to become acting Provost of the University. During that period he also served as Chief Administrator of the College of Dentistry. From 1958 to 1959 he was Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science as well as Washington Square College. In 1962 he was appointed Vice President and Secretary of the University. In September 1967 he was appointed Archivist of the University, a position he held until March 1969. He retired from NYU in 1970.
Pollock was awarded honorary degrees from Muskingum College and the Universities of Brazil and Bahia.
He wrote several books, including The Philadelphia Theatre in the Eighteenth Century, The Teaching of English Grammar in the Secondary Schools of New Jersey, The Nature of Literature, A Theory of Meaning Analyzed, The English Language in American Education, and Thomas Wolfe at Washington Square (with Oscar Cargill). He was working on a 20th-century history of New York University at the time of his retirement. He died of pneumonia May 12, 1988, at the age of 86.
Scope and Contents
This collection contain mostly administrative correspondence and program/department reports. There are extensive notes and minutes from meetings of the TIAA/CREF Board of Trustees (1962-1964), documentation of Dr. Pollock's trips to various academic institutions, records from the Publishing Council of NYU Press, of which Dr. Pollock was a member (1961-1966), and Proposals for the College of Independent Study (1959-1964). General correspondence, memoranda, and event invitations round out the collection.
Custodial history
This collection was maintained by the office of the Vice President and Secretary under the care of Ernest Frederic Knauth, Assistant to the Vice President and Secretary, before it was transferred to the University Archives in 1977.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in a single series, alphabetically by theme and chronologically within those themes.
Related Collection Materials
Records of the Office of the Vice President and Secretary (Harold O. Voorhis), RG 4.0.1.
American Council on Education. Overseas Liaison Committee.; Clark University (Worcester, Mass.).; Hester, James M., 1924-; Indiana University of Pennsylvania.; Johnson, Philip, 1906-2005; Kendall, James; Knauth, Ernest Frederic, 1902-; Munn, James Buell, 1890-1967; Nelson, Norton; New York University. Office of the Vice President and Secretary.; NYU Press.; O'Brien, Conor Cruise, 1917-2008 -- Correspondence; Pollock, Thomas Clark, 1902-1988; Voorhis, Harold O.
- Series I
  - Asian Conservation Laboratory, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - British University Summer Schools, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - British University Summer Schools, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - British University Summer Schools, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - College Retirement Equities Fund (CREF)/Teachers' Insurance and Annuity Association of America (TIAA) Records, Reports, Minutes, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CREF/TIAA Records, Reports, Minutes, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CREF/TIAA Records, Reports, Minutes, January - May, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CREF/TIAA Records, Reports, Minutes, May - December, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CREF/TIAA Records, Reports, Minutes, September - November, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - CREF/TIAA Records, Reports, Minutes, November - December, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CREF/TIAA Records, Reports, Minutes, January - April, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Directory of American Scholars, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Office Memoranda, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hampton Institute Speech, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Installation of Officers in Other Universities, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Invitations, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Invitations, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Invitations, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Johnson, Philip - Washington Square Center Architect, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Kendall, Dr. James C., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Correspondence between Harold O. Voorhis, James B. Munn, and James Kendall regarding a matter of starting a "Mandel scholarship prize" in honor of the late John A. Mandel, Chair of Chemistry.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Bulk, 1965-1966; 1948-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Morton, W. Scott, Executive Director of University Christian Foundation, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - O'Brien, Dr. Conor Cruise (holder of the A. Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities), 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - President's Reception for Faculty Members, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Nelson, Dr. Norton, Provost of University Heights (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publishing Council of NYU Press (Dr. Pollock, member of council), 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Publishing Council of NYU Press, January - September 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Publishing Council of NYU Press, September - November 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Publishing Council of NYU Press, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Publishing Council of NYU Press, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Puerto Rican Cultural Center, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Saint Andrew's Society, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - St. Philip's Community Youth Center, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sao Paulo Foundation School, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Correspondence
  - List of Departmental Secretaries, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Systems Development Corporation, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Trip: 75th Anniversary of Clark University, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Contents
    Expense report.
  - Trip: American Council on Education, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Correspondence, conference program and several issues of "High Education and National Affairs" publication, brochures, expense report.
  - Trip: National Instruction Television Laboratory, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Trip: Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Trip: University of Connecticut Inauguration, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Trip: Muskingum College Inauguration, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Trip: Association of Urban Universities Conference, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Trip: Association of American Colleges Conference, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Trip: Rochester-Cincinnati, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Trip: University of Rochester Inauguration, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Trip: Indiana University, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Trip: Wilton Park, England, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Trip: Wroxton, England, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - University Heights Presbyterian Church, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - College of Independent Study Proposals: 1959, December 1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Brief correspondence and several copies of A Plan for the College for Independent Study dated December 16, 1959.
  - College of Independent Study Proposals: 1960, March 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Policy questions and "Basis for Discussion of Policy Questions related to the Proposal of a College for Independent Study" in several parts.
  - College of Independent Study Proposals: 1960 - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Correspondence and proposal draft, plus notes.
  - CREF/TIAA Records, Reports, Minutes, April - August, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)